Guide to the Pittsburgh Railways Company Records, 1872-1974 AIS.1974.29
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh Railways Company Records
1872-1974
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh Railways Company
AIS.1974.29
23 Linear Feet (16 boxes, 1 map-case folder and 2 map tubes)
These Records consist of reports, appraisals, maps, photographs, ledgers, court proceedings, materials on labor relations, and histories of the Pittsburgh Railways Company (PRC), 1872-1974. The PRC was the largest provider of mass transit in the Pittsburgh area from its creation in 1902 until its demise in 1964, when it was absorbed into the Port Authority of Allegheny County. Digital reproductions of some of the photographs in the collection are available online. Other images of Pittsburgh Railways streetcars can be found online in the Robert G. Pflaum Slide Collection, 1910-2000, AIS.2010.01.
History
Pittsburgh Railways Company (PRC) was originally chartered in 1900 as the Southern Traction Company. By 1902, the PRC became the operating manager of 193 street railway properties owned or controlled by the Philadelphia Company, Consolidated Traction, United Traction and Southern Traction. The latter three companies were merged to form Pittsburgh Railways. By 1910, before the automobile revolutionized urban transportation, Pittsburgh Railways was transporting some 600,000 passengers daily over 581 miles of track. By 1918, its peak year of operation, the company had 606 miles of track accommodating 99 trolley routes. However, largely because of its obligations to investors previously associated with independent streetcar companies, Pittsburgh Railways was in financial difficulty from the outset. Eighteen of its first 50 years were spent in bankruptcy proceedings.
Fares rose from three cents to five cents, then to six cents in 1917 and 10 cents in 1919. In that year, 3,000 motormen and conductors walked off the job after their demands for a 12-cent hourly pay raise were rejected. Pittsburgh Railways Company was under constant pressure from the City administration and Chamber of Commerce to improve service and equipment. Traffic congestion on downtown streets was another major concern, dating back to 1902 when the first of many proposals were made for a downtown subway system. A bond issue to provide $6 million in City funds for subway construction was approved by voters in 1919, and in 1926 City Council was asked to issue $26 million in additional bonds. But these, along with subway plans advocated in 1926 and 1932, were abandoned because of disagreement over routing and conflict and indecision among public officials.
Although beset by continuing financial problems and declining ridership during the depression years, in 1936 and 1937 Pittsburgh Railways placed into service the first 100 Presidents' Conference Cars (PCC) trolleys. By 1949, a total of 666 PCC cars had been purchased. With post-World War II escalation of automobile production, highway construction and suburban growth, transit service, ridership and revenue plummeted at a more rapid rate. In addition, during the 1950s, service was disrupted three times by major labor strikes for prolonged periods, once for nearly two months. Within a 13-year period between January, 1948 and December, 1961, the fare structure was adjusted upward 13 times. The base cash fare increased from 10 to 30 cents on trolleys and from 15 to 35 cents on buses. By 1963, ridership fell to 74.4 million riders. The company was reorganized in 1951 but continued on a course of self-liquidation. During a six-year period through 1960, Pittsburgh Railways' net profit averaged 1.6 percent of its gross revenue. In three of the six years, the company had net losses ranging from $144,000 to $309,000. In 1963, the base wage rate for operators was $2.90 per hour, equal to those in Boston and exceeded only by operators employed by the New York City transit system.
During the 1950s, in addition to Pittsburgh Railways vehicles, 16 independent lines operated buses into downtown Pittsburgh and 21 others provided service to suburban areas. This resulted in intense competition and inadequately maintained and obsolescent rolling equipment. Each line had its own fare structure and there were no transfer privileges between any of the separate bus lines. The Pittsburgh Railways Company operated Pittsburgh's vast electric trolley network until 1964, when the Port Authority of Allegheny County used its power of eminent domain for the first time and assumed control and the railways became part of the Port Authority Transit (PAT) system. In 1967, the remaining companies of the PRC were combined into the Pittway Company.
Scope and Content Notes
The Records of the Pittsburgh Railways Company, 1872-1974, contain reports, proceedings, maps, diagrams, appraisals, labor relations, photographs, ledgers, film, and awards. This collection is organized into twelve series. Series I. contains the Snow Report, submitted in 1919 and covering the years 1872-1917, consists of inventories, historical costs, charts, and photographs of the 193 traction companies consolidated into the Pittsburgh Railways Company in 1902. Series II. contains Condemnation Proceedings, 1964-1966, and consist of appraisals, court exhibits, maps, architectural diagrams, photographs, and tables. Series III. consists of the Pittsburgh Railway's relationship with organized labor, 1949-1963. Series IV. contains the Annual Reports of the Philadelphia Company, Pittsburgh Railways Company, and the Pittway Corporation, 1918-1975. This series also includes the Annual Reports to the Pennsylvania Public Utility Commission, 1950-1963. Series V. contains thirteen volumes of the Official Report of Proceedings before the SEC in re the Indebtedness of the Pittsburgh Railways Company. Series VI. contains Reorganization Proceedings, December 31, 1946. Series VII. contains appraisals of Pittsburgh Railways Company land holdings arising from litigation brought by the City of Pittsburgh and certain other municipalities, 1918-1954. Series VIII. contains one volume of records consisting of the combined plan for reorganization under bankruptcy law, 1949-1950. Series IX. contains photographs of PRC car barns in the 1960s. Series X. contains miscellaneous maps, leases, reports, ledgers, and aerial film footage, 1898-1971. Series XI. contains a collection of safety awards and photographs from Pittsburgh Railways Company originally accessioned earlier as a separate collection but has been combined with this collection as this series. The series also includes pamphlets, maps, copies of stocks, and miscellaneous notes. Series XII consists of maps showing all or part of the Pittsburgh Railways Company track system and a table listing the types of passenger motor and trailer cars used by the company.
Additional descriptions of series are available at the series level.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Pittsburgh Railways Company, June 1, 1964 and October 18, 1974.
Previous Citation
Pittsburgh Railways Company Records, 1872-1974, AIS.1974.29, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Pittsburgh Railways Company, Records, 1872-1966, 1971, ais 74:29, Archives of Industrial Society, University of Pittsburgh Libraries. Parts of this collection have also been cited as: Pittsburgh Railways Safety Awards and Photograph Collection, ais 64:34, Archives of Industrial Society, University of Pittsburgh Libraries
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of some of the photographs in the collection are available online at http://historicpittsburgh.org/collection/pittsburgh-railways-company-records.
Business records; Street-railroads -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- History; Transportation -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- History; Business and Industry; Street-railroads -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County -- Maps; Street-railroads -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Maps; Electric railroads -- Cars -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Tables; Transportation; Pittsburgh Railways Company
- Snow Report, 1872-1917; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I contains the Snow Report. A report of the Engineers Valuation Board in regards to the Pittsburgh Railways Company submitted to the Public Service Commission of the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, August, 1919, by Dr. F. Herbert Snow, chairman of the Engineers Valuation Board.
  The report is the original manuscript from which the published report evolved. These materials provide a complete historical background of the 193 traction companies which existed prior to the establishment of the Pittsburgh Railways Company in 1902, the subsequent development into five companies, and finally consolidated into the Pittsburgh Railways Company.
  The study was designed to determine the value of the properties for rate making purposes. In pursuit of this goal, the Board determined the cost of operation, charges for maintenance, renewals and replacements, improvements, and other costs affecting rates of fare. The study includes an inventory of all the property of the Pittsburgh Railways Company and its affiliates, as well as the original and historical costs of the different properties and underlying systems. Also contains some charts and photographs.
  Thirty one typescript loose leaf volumes, an index, and a ledger cover the years 1872-1917. A table of contents for each volume and companies included in each volume is described at the folder level.
  - Index to Snow Report (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Volume 1 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    Scope and Content Note
    Includes: United Traction Company of Pittsburgh -- Howard East Street Railway -- Bellevue and Perrysville Street Railway Company -- Allegheny, Bellevue and Perrysville Street Railway Company.
  - Volume 2 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    Includes: Allegheny, Evergreen and Millvale Street Railway Company -- Ben Avon and Emsworth Street Railway Company -- Cedar Avenue Street Railway Company -- Corey Avenue Street Railway Company -- East McKeesport Street Railway Company -- Glenwood Highway Bridge Company -- Superior Avenue and Shady Avenue Street Railway Company.
  - Volume 3 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    Includes the North Side Traction Group, consisting of: Federal Street Pleasant Valley Passenger Railway Company -- Park Passenger Railway Company -- Peoples Line Passenger Railway Company -- Peoples Park Passenger Railway Company -- Observatory Hill Passenger Railway Company -- Federal Street Pleasant Valley Passenger Railway Company No. 2 -- Troy Hill Passenger Railway Company -- Allegheny Street Railway Company -- Perry Street Railway Company -- Allegheny and Bellevue Street Railrway Company -- Federal Street Pleasant Valley Passenger Railway Company -- Park Passenger Railway Company -- Peoples Line Passenger Railway Company -- Peoples Park Passenger Railway Company -- Observatory Hill Passenger Railway Company -- Federal Street Pleasant Valley Passenger Railway Company No. 3 -- North End Passenger Railway Company -- North Side Traction Company.
  - Volume 4 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
    Includes the Second Avenue Traction Group, consisting of: Second Avenue Passenger Railway Company No. 1 -- Greenfield Avenue Railway Company -- Second Avenue Passenger Railway Company No. 2 -- Hazelwood, Homestead and Braddock Passenger Railway Company -- Second Avenue Passenger Railway Company No. 3 -- Braddock and Turtle Creek Street Railway Company -- Second Avenue Passenger Railway Company No. 4 -- Pittsburgh, Glenwood and Homestead Passenger Street Railway Company -- Turtle Creek Valley Electric Railway Company -- Homestead Street Railway Company -- Second Avenue Tractions Company.
  - Volume 5 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Includes: McKeesport Passenger Railway Company -- Dravosburg, Reynoldton and McKeesport Passenger Railway Company -- Dravosburg Electric Railway Company -- Pittsburgh and Homestead Electric Street Railway Company -- Glenwood-Dravosburg Electric Street Railway Company No. 2 -- Glenwood-Dravosburg Electric Street Railway Company No. 3 -- Second Avenue Traction Company.
  - Volume 6 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
    Includes: Pittsburgh, Allegheny and Manchester Railway Company -- Union Passenger Railway Company -- Pittsburgh Union Passenger Railway Company No. 1 -- Pittsburgh Union Passenger Railway Company No. 2 -- Pittsburgh, Allegheny and Manchester Traction Company.
  - Volume 7 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
    Includes the Pittsburgh Birmingham Traction Company System, consisting of: Pittsburgh Birmingham Passenger Railway Company -- Pittsburgh and Ormsby Passenger Railroad Company -- South Side Passenger Railroad Company -- Mount Oliver Incline Railway Company -- Pittsburgh Incline Plane Company -- Pittsburgh, Knoxville and St. Clair Street Railroad Company.
  - Volume 8 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
    Includes: Birmingham Street Railway Company -- Hilltop Railway Company -- Birmingham, Knoxville and Allentown Traction Company -- Brownsville Avenue Street Railway Company -- West Liberty Street Railway Company -- Pittsburgh Birmingham Traction Company.
  - Volume 9 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
    Includes: Pittsburgh and Charleroi Street Railway Group.
  - Volume 10 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Includes: Pittsburgh Railway Company -- Virginia Avenue Street Railway Company -- McKees Rocks and Ingram Street Railway Company -- Southern Traction Company.
  - Volume 11 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Includes the West End Traction Group, which consists of: Pittsburgh West End Railway Company -- Pittsburgh and Temperanceville Railway Company -- Pittsburgh and McKees Rocks Railway Company -- Pittsburgh, Neville Island and Coraopolis Railway Company.
  - Volume 12 (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
    Includes: Coraopolis and Neville Island Bridge Company -- Pittsburgh, Crafton and Mansfield Street Railway Company -- Carnegie, Heidelberg and Bridgeville Street Railway Company -- West End, Mt. Washington and Banksville Street Railway Company -- West End Traction Company.
  - Volume 13 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes: Sycamore Street Railway Company -- Mt. Washington Street Railway Company No. 1 -- Mt. Washington Street Railway Company No. 2 -- Pittsburgh Tunnel Company -- Mt. Washington Tunnel Company.
  - Volume 14 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
    Includes: McKees Rocks & Neville Island Street Railway Company -- Crafton and Chartiers Valley Traction Company -- Pittsburgh, Banksville & Mt. Lebanon Street Railway Company -- Carnegie Bridge Company -- Southern Traction Company.
  - Volume 15 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    Includes: Pittsburgh and Castle Shannon Railroad Company.
  - Volume 16 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Volume 17 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Includes: Washington & Canonsburg Railway Company -- Bethel Street Railway Company -- Mount Bethel Street Railway Company -- Canonsburg and Upper St. Clair Street Railway Company -- Pittsburgh, Canonsburg and Washington Railway Company.
  - Volume 18 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
    Includes: Pittsburgh Express Company -- Ambridge, Dixmont and Emsworth Street Railway Company -- Pittsburgh Southern Street Railway Company -- Frankstown Avenue Extension Street Railway Company -- Washington and Claysville Street Railway Company -- Bon Air Street Railway Company -- Rosslyn Street Railway Company -- Clairton Street Railway Company -- Clairton and Blair Street Railway Company -- Pine Run Street Railway Company.
  - Volume 19 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Includes: West Liberty Suburban Street Railway Company -- McKees Rocks and Allegheny Street Railway Company -- Grant and Liberty Street Railway Company -- Bates Street Railway Company -- Carrick and Baldwin Street Railway Company -- Brereton Avenue Street Railway Company.
  - Volume 20 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
    Includes: Consolidated Traction Company -- Morningside Electric Street Railway Company -- Lacock Street Railway Company -- Park Avenue Street Railway Company -- Duquesne Gardens Company -- West Braddock Bridge Company -- Ardmore Street Railway Company.
  - Volume 21 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
    Includes: Central Traction Company -- Pittsburgh and Minersville Passenger Railway Company -- Central Passenger Railway Company of Pittsburgh -- Central Passenger Railway Company -- Central Traction Company.
  - Volume 22 (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
    Includes: Pittsburgh Traction Company -- Pittsburgh and East Liberty Passenger Railway Company -- Oakland Railway Company -- Pittsburgh, Oakland and East Liberty Passenger Railway Company -- Central Transit Company -- Bloomfield Street Railway Company -- Bellefield Street Railway Company -- Pittsburgh Traction Company.
  - Volume 23 (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
    Includes the Duquesne Traction Group, which consists of: Wilkinsburgh and East Libery Railway Company -- East End Street Railway Company -- Larimer Street Railway Company -- Craig Street Railway Company -- Howe Street Railway Company -- Boyd Street Railway Company -- Highland Street Railway Company -- Market Street Railway Company -- Peoples Street Railway Company -- Wilkinsburg Street Railway Company -- Duquesne Street Railway Company No. 1 -- Duquesne Street Railway Company No. 2 -- Grant Street Railway Company.
  - Volume 24 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Includes: Dusquesne Traction Company.
  - Volume 25 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
    Includes the Fort Pitt Traction Group, which consists of: Citizens Passenger Railway Company -- Transverse Passenger Railway Company No. 1 -- Transverse Passenger Railway Company No. 2 -- Transverse Passenger Railway Company No. 3 -- North Side Passenger Railway Company -- Penn Street Railway Company -- Aspinwall Street Railway Company -- Highland Park and Butler Street Railway Company -- Citizens Traction Company.
  - Volume 26 (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
    Includes: Allegheny Traction Company -- Millvale, Etna and Sharpburg Street Railway Company -- Fort Pitt Street Railway Company -- Gross Street Railway Company -- Negley Street Railway Company -- Highland Park Passenger Railway Company -- Fort Pitt Traction Company.
  - Volume 27 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Includes: Monongahela Street Railway Company -- Squirrel Hill Railroad Company -- Schenley Park and Highlands Railway Company -- Homestead and Highlands Street Railway Company.
  - Volume 27 (copy) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Volume 28 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Includes: Braddock and Homestead Street Railway Company, including one underlying company (Braddock and Duquesne Bridge Company) -- Braddock and Duquesne Street Railway Company, including two underlying companies (Monongahela Boulevard Company and Thompson's Run Bridge Company) -- Monongahela Street Railway Company No. 1 -- Monongahela Street Railway Company No. 2, including two underlying companies (McKeesport and West Elizabeth Street Railway Company and Blair & Port Vue Street Railway Company).
  - Volume 29 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
    Includes: Wilkinsburg and East Pittsburgh Railway Company No. 1, including one underlying company (Braddock and North Homestead Street Railway Company) -- Braddock Electric Railway Company -- North Braddock Street Railway Company -- Edgewood and Swissvale Street Railway Company -- Wilkinsburg and East Pittsburgh Street Railway Company No. 2 -- Pittsburgh and Swissvale Street Railway Company No. 1 -- Homewood Street Railway Company -- Pittsburgh and Swissvale Street Railway Company No. 2 -- Wilkinsburg and East Pittsburgh Street Railway Company No. 3.
  - Volume 30 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
    Includes: Wilkinsburg and Verona Street Railway Company -- Wilmerding and Pitcairn Street Railway Company -- Pitcairn and Westmoreland Street Railway Company -- Pitcairn and Wilmerding Street Railway Company -- Monongahela Street Railway Company No. 3.
  - Volume 31 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
    Includes the Suburban Rapid Transit Street Railway Group, which consists of: Suburban Rapid Transit Street Railway Company No. 1 -- Suburban Rapid Transit Street Railway Company No. 2 -- South Twenty-Second Street Railway Company -- Suburban Rapid Transit Street Railway Company.
- Condemnation Proceedings, 1964-1966; II.
  Series II contains texts of the proceedings in the Court of Common Pleas, Allegheny County, Pennsylvania, regarding petition of the Port of Allegheny County Authority (PAT) for appointment of viewers to determine and assess damages by reason of the condemnation of Pittsburgh Railways Company's (PRC) Transportation System, April term, 1964. This series consists of typescript of 17,727 pages in 99 volumes; four binders of typescript loose leaf pages appraising the value of Pittsburgh Railways Company properties (including extensive use of maps and photographs); and 563 PAT and PRC exhibits used in conjunction with the court proceedings. These exhibits contain typescript pages, maps, architectural diagrams, photographs and tables. Maps, including those used in the 1966 appraisal of the PRC, are also included in this series.
  Inventories and indexes to the PAT and PRC exhibits are located at the beginning of each exhibit list as well as within each individual file folder containing exhibits.
  - Proceedings, 1.
    - Volume 1-7 (Box 3, Folder 9-21)
    - Volume 8-23 (Box 4, Folder 1-25)
    - Volume 23-61 (Box 5, Folder 1-29)
    - Volume 62-102 (Box 6, Folder 1-21)
    - Corrections to Typographical Errors (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Draft Outline, May 3, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - John K. Ellis Appraisal, 2.
    - Parcels 2-1 to 16-2 (Box 6, Folder 24-25)
    - Parcels 17.2 to 13.1 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Parcels 17.2 to 13.1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Parcels A1 to R2 (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
    - Parcels Roadway South Hills (Box 7, Folder 4-5)
  - PAT Exhibits, 3.
    - Index and Exhibit 1-25 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Exhibit 26-50 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Exhibit 51-75 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Exhibit 76-84 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Exhibit 85-94 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Exhibit 95-99 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Exhibit 100-107 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Exhibit 108 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Exhibit 109-120 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Exhibit 121-130 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Exhibit 131-140 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Exhibit 141-149 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Exhibit 150-168 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Exhibit 169 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Exhibit 170-184 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Exhibit 185-195 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Exhibit 196-202 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Exhibit 203-206 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Exhibit 208-211 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Exhibit 212-224 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Exhibit 225-237 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Exhibit 1001-1005 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Exhibit 1006-1039 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Exhibit 1040-1048 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Exhibit 1049-1058 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Exhibit 1060-1079 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Exhibit 1080 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Exhibit 1080-1098 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - PRC Exhibits, 4.
    - Index and Exhibit 9-11 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Exhibit 12 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Exhibit 12 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
    - Exhibit 13-34 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Exhibit 35 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Exhibit 36-110 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Exhibit 111-128 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Exhibit 129-142 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Exhibit 143-156 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Exhibit 157-171 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Exhibit 172-188 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Exhibit 189-195 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Exhibit 196-205 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Exhibit 206-222 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Exhibit 223-236 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Exhibit 237 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Exhibit 140-141 (Film Housed Separately) (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - PRC Exhibit Book I (Box 9, Folder 17-18)
    - Deeds to Part I of Land Exhibit (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Deeds to Part II of Land Exhibit (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Labor Relations, 1949-1963; III.